A Guide to the Women's Christian Temperance Union of Virginia Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #1750
Women's Christian Temperance Union of Virginia Papers 1882-1958
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
Collection number 1750
365 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection (# 1750 ) was put on deposit 1938-1953.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 365 items (3.5 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1.5 linear shelf feet), 1882-1958, papers of the Woman's Christian Temperance Union (Women's Christian Temperance Union) of Virginia, a women's organization whose purpose was to prevent the sale and consumption of alcohol in Virginia. The collection is arranged in three series: I. Correspondence and History File, II. Convention Programs and Proceedings, Publications, Photographs, Memorabilia, and Scrapbook, III. Bound Volumes and Printed Materials.
The correspondence includes letters to Amy C. Weech, Director of the Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union Evangelistic Department and Mrs. Mrs. Walter [Maude] H. Page, Vice-President of the Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union during the period in which the 18th amendment was repealed and includes a letter from Governor John Garland Pollard. The history file includes a Governor's Proclamation of Youth Temperance Education Week by Governor William A. Tuck. The major portion of the collection consists of minute books of state conventions and local union business meetings from 1882-1958. The scrapbook consists of Women's Christian Temperance Union literature produced by the Fair and Exhibits Department.
Organizational History
The Woman's Christian Temperance Union of Virginia was founded January 2, 1883, five years after the first local union was organized at Lincoln, Virginia. The object of the Women's Christian Temperance Union was to organize local unions throughout the state in order to eliminate liquor sales and production. The first efforts of the Women's Christian Temperance Union were to secure legislative adoption of the Local Option Law to enable localities to individually vote on the sale of liquor in each. The Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union successfully agitated for the Scientific Temperance Instruction Law which mandated a temperance curriculum in state public schools. The Women's Christian Temperance Union worked for National Prohibition which occurred with the passage of the Eighteenth Amendment in 1920. Though dismayed by the repeal of Prohibition in 1933, the Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union continued to work for temperance, especially among Virginia's youth, and broadened its reform program beyond temperance, taking stands against gambling, poor working conditions, and smoking through educational and legislative activities.
Alderman Library holdings include a variety of collections on the Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union. Provenance: See individual accession numbers for provenance information.
Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union State Presidents
Mrs. William H. Pleasants, 1883, Jan.-Oct.
Mrs. Rebecca D. Wilson, 1883-1866.
Mrs. William H. Pleasants, 1886-1888.
Mrs. R. H. Jones, 1888-1898.
Mrs. Howard M. Hoge, 1898-1938.
Mrs. Amy C. Weech, 1938-1942.
Mrs. Herbert W. Phillips, 1942-1950.
Mrs. Roy T. Jarrett, 1950-1958.
Container List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE AND HISTORY FILE
  - Correspondence of Amy C. Weech>, Director, Va. Women's Christian Temperance Union Evangelistic Dept., 1930-1936, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Mrs. Walter H. Page, Vice-President of Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1935-1937, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - History File of Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1882, 1905, 1917, 1937-1949, n.d. (Box Box 1)
- SERIES II: CONVENTION PROGRAMS AND PROCEEDINGS, PUBLICATIONS, PHOTOGRAPHS, MEMORABILIA, AND SCRAPBOOK
  - Convention Programs of Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1903-1958 (Box Box 1)
  - Fifty-ninth Annual Convention of Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, Miscellaneous material, Report, Minutes, 1941 (Box Box 1)
  - Sixtieth Annual Convention of the Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, Copy Proof of Report and Minutes, 1942 (Box Box 1)
  - Publication: Union Signal(>National Women's Christian Temperance Union), 1912, 1915 (Box Box 1)
  - Local Union Directory, Pamphlets and Newsletter, Prize Essays, 1943-1947, 1957, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Photographs, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1895, 1936-1942, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Women's Christian Temperance Union Scrapbook, prepared by Director of Fairs and Exhibits, ca.1940-1942 (Box Box 2)
  - Material removed from Women's Christian Temperance Union Scrapbook, ca.1940-1942 (Box Box 2)
  - Anti-Monroe Doctrine Society, 1945-1948 (Box Box 2)
- SERIES III: BOUND VOUMES AND PRINTED MATERIAL
  - Bound Vol. 1: Minutes, Richmond, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1882-1885 (Box Box 2)
  - Bound Vol. 2: Minutes, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union Convention, 1883 (Box Box 2)
  - Bound Vol. 3: Minutes, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union Convention, 1887 (Box Box 2)
  - Bound Vol. 4: Minutes, Newport News, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1903-1906 (Box Box 2)
  - Bound Vol. 5: Minutes, Central Union, Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1906-1908 (Box Box 2)
  - Bound Vol. 6: Minutes, Marshall/Woodward Union, Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1906-1909 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 7: Minutes, Woodard Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1909-1910 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 8: Minutes, Bridgewater, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1911-1917 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 9: Minutes, Central Union (Roanoke, Virginia) Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1912-1916 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 10: Minutes, Charlottesville, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1936-1942 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 11: Minutes, Charlottesville, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1942-1945 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 12: Minutes, Elizabeth City-Warwick Bi-County Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1942-1952 (Box Box 3)
  - Bound Vol. 13: Minutes, Tri-City Women's Christian Temperance Union, 1957-1958 (Box Box 3)
  - Except from Memories of the Crusade by Mother Stewart, 1889 (Box Box 4)
  - Statue of Miss Frances E. Willard (Proceedings of Dedication), 1905 (Box Box 4)
  - Virginia Call, 1931-1939 (Box Box 4)
  - The Light-house: A History of Richmond-Henrico County Women's Christian Temperance Union 1882-1935, 1938 (Box Box 4)
  - Reports and Minutes, Virginia Women's Christian Temperance Union Convention, 1948 (Box Box 4)